<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="">
  <para>QWI and Job-to-Job Flow Shapefile Data  </para>
  <para>Shapefiles used to provide mapping functionality in QWI Explorer and Job-to-Job Explorer are created by transforming input shapefiles sourced from TIGER/Line. Text below describes the inputs, transformations, and the output shapefiles.</para>
  <para/>
  <para>INPUTS</para>
  <para>Source:  TIGER/Line 2015 shapefiles (<ulink url="https://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/tiger-line.html">https://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/tiger-line.html</ulink>).  </para>
  <para>Input shapefiles:</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="ftp://ftp2.census.gov/geo/tiger/TIGER2015/STATE/">tl_2015_us_state</ulink>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <anchor id="_GoBack"/>
        <ulink url="ftp://ftp2.census.gov/geo/tiger/TIGER2015/COUNTY/">tl_2015_us_county</ulink>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="ftp://ftp2.census.gov/geo/tiger/TIGER2015/CBSA/">tl_2015_us_cbsa</ulink>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><ulink url="ftp://ftp2.census.gov/geo/tiger/TIGER2015/PLACE/">tl_2015_[ST]_place</ulink> (for creation of WIA/WIB shapefile)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><ulink url="ftp://ftp2.census.gov/geo/tiger/TIGER2015/COUSUB/">tl_2015_[ST]_cousub</ulink> (for creation of WIA/WIB shapefile)</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para/>
  <para>TRANSFORMATIONS</para>
  <para>The following major transformations are applied to the input files:  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>All geographies are reprojected to WGS-1984 Geographic Coordinate System (<ulink url="http://spatialreference.org/ref/epsg/wgs-84/">http://spatialreference.org/ref/epsg/wgs-84/</ulink>).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Shoreline water has been clipped out to provide a more recognizable depiction of the coastlines.  </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Each layer is given internal point coordinates (stored as double) based on the WGS-1984 projection (decimal degrees).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Each layer is run through a “simplify polygon” procedure to remove unnecessary complexity from the features. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Features from Guam, American Samoa, and the Northern Mariana Islands have been removed because they are not used current LEHD tabulations. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Each shapefile’s attribute table has been updated to conform to the standard LEHD output format (<ulink url="http://lehd.ces.census.gov/data/schema/latest/variables_shp.csv">variables_shp.csv</ulink>), which consists of the following six fields: STUSPS, GEOGRAPHY, NAME, LABEL, INTPTLAT and INTPTLON.   Legal values for STUSPS can be found in <ulink url="http://lehd.ces.census.gov/data/schema/latest/label_stusps.csv">label_stusps.csv</ulink>.  </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para/>
  <para>OUTPUTS</para>
  <para>Output shapefiles – grouped by paired products – are listed below. Each shapefile includes specific notes on its preparation.</para>
  <para/>
  <para>QWI Geographies</para>
  <para>State (lehd_state.shp)</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>No transformations occur to this layer other than those listed above.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>County (lehd_county.shp)</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>STUSPS is added to the NAME field so that county names read: "Cook, IL" for example.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>CBSA - within State (lehd_stcbsa.shp) </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>All features are split into state-specific CBSA features by intersecting each feature with the state shapefile features.  </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The STUSPS field is added during the intersect with the state shapefile.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>STFIPS (i.e. numeric nationally unique state code) is prepended to the GEOGRAPHY field to distinguish state-parts of the same CBSA (i.e. make them nationally unique). </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>“([STUSPS] part)” is added to the end of the NAME field only for those CBSA features that are split by state lines.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>Workforce Investment Board Areas (lehd_wib.shp)</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>The WIA/WIB shapefiles are built from the Place, County Subdivision, and County shapefiles from TIGER/Line based on definitions provided by the LED state partners.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para/>
  <para>Job-to-Job Flow Geographies</para>
  <para>State (lehd_state.shp)</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>No transformations occur to this layer (the same state file is used for QWI and J2J applications).</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>CBSA - National (lehd_cbsa.shp)</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>The state remainder areas are added to the shapefile as new features.  They are assigned unique codes ([STUSPS]+999) and names (“Not in metro/micro area, [STUSPS]”).</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</article>
